İzmir (Smyrna) postcards and photographs collection RL.11867
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
İzmir (Smyrna) postcards and photographs collection
approximately 1890-1950
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11867
0.25 Linear Feet 1 half-size Hollinger box
Collection is a set of postcards (including photograph postcards) from late 19th and 20th century Turkey, depicting scenes and people in İzmir (Smyrna), Turkey. Materials have been individually numbered and described in English, French, and Turkish.
Content Description
Collection consists of individual postcards and photographs of İzmir (Smyrna), dating from the late 1800s through the 1950s. Some postcards are blank; others have been mailed and contain correspondence most often in French, Greek, or Ottoman-Turkish. Images depicted vary but include markets, mosques, streets and houses, harbor scenes, piers, the clock tower. A subset of images depicts the Great Fire of 1922 from the Greco-Turkish War, Greek refugees fleeing by boat, and a floating corpse. There are images of both people and methods of transportation.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The İzmir (Smyrna) Postcards and Photographs Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2019.
Biographical / Historical
İzmir, also known in Greek as Smyrna (sometimes Smyrne) is a Levantine port city now part of present-day Turkey. As a major Levantine city in the Eastern Mediterranean, İzmir was home to a wide variety of people most prominently Armenians, Greeks, Jews, and Turks. Recent tumultuous history has dramatically altered the formerly cosmopolitan make-up of the city. A significant contributing factor was the Population Exchange between 1919-1923. In addition, the Great Fire of 1922 ruined much of the traditional architecture of the city which reflected the diversity of former inhabitants.
Historical note authored by Sean Swanick, Dec. 2020.
Izmir, Gulf of (Turkey); Greece -- Photographs; Greece -- Civilization -- Turkish influences; Greco-Turkish War, 1921-1922; Turkey -- Pictorial works.; Turkey -- History; İzmir (Turkey) -- Pictorial works; İzmir (Turkey) -- History -- Fire, 1922; İzmir (Turkey) -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Turkey -- Description and travel; Turkey -- History -- 20th century; İzmir (Turkey) -- Ethnic relations
- 1922 Fire: İzmir (Smyrne) yangını / Izmir (Smyrna) Fire (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-001)
- 1922 Fire: İzmir (Smyrne) yangını sonrası, Osmanlı ve Rum tipler beraber sahil'de / Izmir (Smyrna) after the fire, Ottoman and Greek types together on the bank (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-002)
- 1922 Fire: İzmir (Smyrne) yangını sonrası, İzmir'i gemilerle terkeden Rum mülteciler / Izmir (Smyrna) after the fire, Greek refugees leaving Izmir by ship (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-003)
- 1922 Fire: İzmir (Smyrne) yangını sonrası, İzmir'i gemilerle terkeden Rum mültecilerin gemisinden geçtikleri güzergahdan görünüş / Izmir (Smyrna) after the fire, view of the Greek refugees route leaving İzmir by ships (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-004)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Torbalı'da bayram günü / Izmir (Smyrna) Bayram (Feast/festival) day in Torbalı (district of Izmir), 1901 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-005)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Türk mahallesi omnibus / Izmir (Smyrna) Omnibuses in a Turkish neighbourhood, 1900 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-006)
- İşgal dönemi (Greek occupation in Anatolia) İzmir, Eskişehir, Afyon civarları, Garde d'un pont / Greek occupation in Anatolia: Izmir, Eskişehir, around Afyon, guarding a bridge, approximately 1920 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-007)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Bayraklı (district in Izmir), 1900s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-008)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Frank caddesi / İzmir (Smyrna) European street, approximately 1910s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-009)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Karşıyaka - Cordelio, approximately 1900s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-010)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Genel görünüş / Izmir (Smyrna), general view, 1907 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-011)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Karşıyaka, Deniz hamamı / İzmir (Smyrna) Karşıyaka (district of Izmir), sea-bathhouses, approximately 1890s-1920s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-012)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Karşıyaka vapur iskelesi / Izmir (Smyrna) Karşıyaka wharf/pier, 1910s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-013)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Saat kulesi / Izmir (Smyrna) Clock tower, 1917 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-014)
- İzmir (Smyrne), Les bazars / Izmir (Smyrna), the market, approximately 1890s-1920 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-015)
- İzmir (Smyrne) le port - liman Ed. Sabetay Cohen / Izmir (Smyrne) the port Ed. Sabetay Cohen, approximately 1890s-1920 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-016)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Partie du Quais / Izmir (Smyrna) The Port, approximately 1890-1920 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-017)
- İzmir (Smyrne) Les Quais / Izmir (Smyrna) The Port, approximately 1890-1920 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-018)
- Floating corpse (possibly from 1922 Fire and aftermath?), approximately 1920s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-019)
- Group of men with tents (perhaps military), approximately 1890s-1920s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-020)
- Smyrne: Forgerons ambulants / Smyrna: Blacksmiths, approximately 1890s-1920s (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-021)
- Smyrne: Campement de Yiourouks (Nomades) / Nomad camp, approximately 1890s-1950 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-022)
- Smyrne: Le Fameux Mustapha Eifendi, approximately 1890s-1950 (Box 1, Item RL-11867-P-023)